Joel Goodman: Tired of
all the AI slop leaders.
This is Higher Ed Hot Takes.
And I'm Joel Goodman.
I am delighted to be joined this
time by my good friend Shane Baglini.
Shane Baglini: Hey, Joel.
Good to see you
Joel Goodman: AI has infiltrated
everything that we do.
Shane Baglini: It has.
Joel Goodman: In higher education and
we've been back channeling a bit over the
weeks as we see things that pop up in our
LinkedIns and every other place online and
thought it might be good to just have a
conversation from the viewpoint of someone
that is inside a college, you know, has
worked inside institutions for years.
While I've been working outside of
institutions and maybe just bring a little
bit more grounding to this conversation
around how we can actually use large
language models in this technology in
ways that are helpful and not harmful.
And maybe just call out some of
those harmful areas that we think
we're seeing across the industry.
'cause there's, there's a lot.
Um.
This was kind of initially
kicked off by a, a couple of
different comments we saw online.
Um, some very hot takes.
We've seen from friends, from colleagues,
from vendors that are all the things
I've been talking about on this show
for the last several, several months.
I.
Shane Baglini: My first take is
this conversation might come off
As you know, we're against ai.
Not the case.
I, I use it every day.
I've used it today.
I'll use it tomorrow.
I think it's incredibly useful and
helpful and a great resource and
tool that everybody should, should
use and should experiment with
and see, see what they figure out.
I, I mean, I'm still
finding new ways to use it.
I'm still finding new things that it can
do and the possibilities are are great.
I think the thing that I would take issue
with, and I think one of the problems that
higher ed practitioners have is this idea
that if you're not advanced in AI or if
you're not using AI assistance or don't
have an AI chat bot, or if you haven't
optimized your entire website, you have
for AI search, that you're somehow behind
the sort of the, the onslaught of ai.
Quote unquote thought leadership is this
sort of, um, and I'm, it's not purposely
making people feel that way, but it, it.
It does, and I see it
all the time on LinkedIn.
I hear it from colleagues, you
know, I feel like I'm behind on ai.
I see all these people doing these great
things, and the reality of it is higher
ed practitioners, including myself, simply
don't have the time to do these things.
And so hearing from people that are
genuinely thought leaders, both in and
outside of higher ed, it sort of is,
is wearing on me this, this constant,
you need to be using AI in this way.
You can do this with AI
and, and really there's.
Only a few practical things that I
see throughout the week that actually
would work for higher ed practitioners.
And so that's kind of where you and
I have been chatting about this,
that, you know, it's great, but
how does higher ed implement it and
where do we get the time to do it?
Joel Goodman: I think there's,
there's a multi-layered issue, right?
I think there's been so much hype,
even just outside of our own circles,
around the ways to use this technology.
A lot of that hype is unfounded.
A lot of that hype is really just to sell.
Subscriptions.
A lot of that hype is, I think,
detrimental to the quality levels
of the, of the work that we produce
and the output that we have.
I think it's detrimental to parts
of society, and I've talked about,
talked about that on this show.
And then there's the follow the leader
style that higher Ed seems to have and
has always had, where the thought leaders,
or as I've been calling them, the AI slop
leaders within the industry, it was within
our industry, within a lot of industry.
They're following those
hype cycles, right?
And then part of that is because
you've got people that are just kinda
like cheerleaders for it, regardless.
I don't know what their motivations
are, but they're cheerleaders.
Other people are just making money on it.
Usually those are the vendors, usually
those are the founders of these
companies that are putting the hard
sell on institutions and convincing
them that they have a solution for a
problem that does not exist, but telling
people they have this problem, right?
And that constant spin and cycle of
hype and pressure and filling of any
empty space in the, in the discourse
and the conversation with this
information, I think does put that.
Downward pressure on people to think,
oh, I have to do this, which is really
strange to me for an industry that has
traditionally been so risk averse that
they would think that jumping into a
technology that is as young as it is with
as many faults as it has, the, the amount
of misinformation that gets generated
by large language models, the, you know,
the so-called hallucinations, which.
Really hallucinations is just
how it's programmed to do it.
You know, the mistakes that are made in
that, and then the lack of criticality
on the side of a lot of people that
are using these tools, they don't, you
know, they think, well, yeah, it seems
good to me, and especially if you don't.
Know how to course correct for
something like that, right?
Like how do you fix that?
Caused this extremely traditional
industry that we've worked in for years
to all of a sudden abandon all of the
criticality and thoughtfulness and
careful and just start throwing money at
it and, and I don't know if that's due
to all of the pressure surrounding it.
Maybe everyone's out of ideas.
Maybe no one really feels like they
know how to do their job anyway.
And so like that's,
that's what the change is.
But those are the things that
worry me because we're replacing
work that we know works.
The thoughtfulness and the expertise
that we have, that our colleagues
have with something that's supposed
to automate it, but we're automating
the wrong parts, in my opinion.
We're automating the stuff that like we
as humans should still be working on.
Shane Baglini: I think, I think there's
a lot that AI can, can do for us.
So two things on what you just said,
the, the, the things that humans can do.
Right.
You and I were going back and forth on
this, the CEO of perplexity talking about
their browser taking over recruiter jobs.
And when I read the headline, I mean, I
read the article that the headline to me
was just, I'm not a recruiter, obviously.
It, it's just insulting to
the profession of a recruiter.
You know, my current position at William
and Mary, I worked with a recruiter.
She was outstanding.
She was the best recruiter
I've ever worked with.
She had insights into the organization
that were incredibly helpful, including,
you know, things like personality fit,
institutional fit, and to say that your
browser can replace what this recruiter
did for me in that process is insane.
There's a lot of uses for ai.
That's not one of them like that is
Joel Goodman: Yeah.
Well, and it's a huge
overstatement too, right?
It's, it's an overstatement to
think that a flawed software program
is better than flawed humans.
At least humans can course correct.
The flawed software is programmed
to do that sort of thing.
And so like I, this has been bugging
me like it's because it shows up.
This is a, I think this
is a great example of it.
Like we are so content to get 70 or
80% of the way there with software when
before that would've been inexcusable.
If we as ourselves, were only
doing 70 or 80% to progress our
institutions to progress, our
marketing, to progress, whatever.
We'd be fired.
Like that's, you know, it's fine
'cause computers are doing it.
Um, but no one backfills
the other 20% in most cases.
I mean, sometimes people do, but
like in most cases like that, other
20 percent's not getting backfilled.
And when you're trying to automate
things like a recruiter's job
that requires soft skills, right?
Like it requires those interpersonal
skills that you really can't, you can't
get out of a predictive text model.
Shane Baglini: No, and it, you know,
I think it unearths a bigger problem,
um, website as a second impression.
And, you know, these AI like chatbots
and things like that, that are
overlaying your already existing
websites and things like that.
And, you know, the idea of this
recruiter perplexity situation, it's
like scanning LinkedIn for qualified
candidates is not replacing a recruiter.
It's a tool for a recruiter.
The same way.
AI is a tool for our websites, for
our marketing, for our messaging.
The, the bigger issue that's getting
covered up and we're trying to bandaid
with AI is that most of our websites
stink and the information is not good.
And so asking AI to correct
that or using AI to mask that
is exacerbating your issue.
If you're reliant on AI search and
then students get to your website
with maybe higher intent, who knows?
And your website stinks.
Joel Goodman: Yeah.
Shane Baglini: It doesn't matter if
you showed up in the search results.
It it, it doesn't matter because
if the student can't find what
they want when they get there,
they're going to say, okay, great.
That came up in the AI results.
Let me move on to the next institution.
Joel Goodman: Right.
If your content's bad, if your website's
not organized properly, that 80% that the
a that the AI tool gets you to helping
them decreases, uh, you know, it's a, it's
a garbage and garbage out sort of deal.
To your point around man AI site
searching, I've been having this
conversation with a lot of people that
are producing these products right now.
I'm like, AI site search.
Or conversational site searches.
A lot of people are calling
it on websites, I think again,
gets you a certain way there.
But remember when all those
snippets started showing up in
Google searches originally, and
we were all like, this sucks.
This is awful.
This is a terrible experience.
But then we put 'em on our websites like
we're, you know, and to your point, it's
like we're serving up the information,
we're summarizing something on the
website, which one means like the content
on our website must not be very important.
And so like.
Maybe question how much content's
on your website if a summary is
enough to give people what they need.
But two, those summaries
don't lead to actions.
They answer a question.
The person leaves your website, they
may never come back, you know, and
so you're leaving a lot to chance.
It's like kind of the exact opposite.
Conversion rate optimization practices.
If you're going to summarize something or
provide an answer, you need to provide an
action as a next step for someone to do.
And these tools don't do that yet.
It's like a huge oversight
by the producers of these,
of these site search tools.
And I keep telling them like.
People don't come to your
university website or your college
website to just be informed.
And if they are doing that, like
you're doing your job wrong because
you need to turn them from people that
are learning about your institution
to people that are interacting and
building affinity with your institution.
And that means getting them to take
actions and connect with you, but they
don't, you know, that gets glossed over.
And unless you're a UX designer,
unless you're someone that is deep
in the weeds of how this stuff works.
In a web interface, you're
probably not thinking about it
when you get that sales pitch.
I, I think it, it just highlights
one of the, one of the missing
pieces to this, put AI in everything
at all costs, mentality that we
see just cropping up in culture.
Shane Baglini: And I think
another point on the.
Google search AI stuff is that, go look at
the sources of most of the search results
coming up, and what you're gonna find is
Reddit and Quora and other public sites
that you can't control the information on.
So if your website is not in order, if
the experience that students are having
when they get to your website is a bad
one, it only compounds the problem because
there's gonna be information that this AI
is pulling from that you can't control.
What you can control
is the user experience.
Once somebody gets to your
website, how you're leading them
to some sort of conversion action.
The messaging of your brand, the,
the usefulness of the materials that
you're providing people, those are
things that AI at the moment can't do.
It's on you to sort of build the
foundation and then see how AI can
enhance it rather than understanding
that we've got a problem.
Maybe our website is old, maybe
there's too, you know, it's become
a repository type of situation.
Let's have AI fix it by having
us show up and search results is
not solving your core problem.
Joel Goodman: Yeah, I, I think if
anything, this sort of underscores
the systemic problems we've had in
web marketing, digital marketing
across the, the sector forever, ever.
And if you know those summaries are
drawing from sources that are not
your website or are not people that.
Have had good experiences with you or
have not had a positive interaction
or you know, a reason to talk
like good about your institution.
That's not an AI problem.
You know, an AI's not gonna fix it.
Like that's a systemic problem within
how you're operating as a brand, how
you're operating your student experience,
and touch points that people have
as they come into your institution.
I fear.
That despite that being the
truth, the answer still becomes
like, yes, but AI will fix.
All of those things for you.
And then the question is, how
does it fix it lie for you?
Like, is it, is it going to make things
up because that is what it does and
that that becomes, you know, a bigger
issue and, and it becomes a bigger
issue That is in line with how the
slop economy kind of works in general.
You know, when you're seeing images and
videos and you can't tell if they're
generated by a model or if they're real.
Slop.
If you're reading content that
doesn't quite make sense or you
can't tell if you know if it's
supposed to be that generic or not.
Like that's slop.
If everything that we're doing is just
kind of regurgitating and cycling through
the same models over and over and over
again, that's just building up on lop and
it presents a real opportunity for those
that in this industry want to take it.
And that's to be human again.
That's to.
Have a point of view that is not the
median of all of the content that
has been used to train these models.
Set yourself apart.
You don't have to play into it.
Going back to your earlier point,
if you feel behind, you don't
have to play into this like.
Think critically when you can
about how to use these tools.
Where I use these tools is for analysis.
I think it's good for data analysis.
It's good for finding
patterns in what you're doing.
You know, if you wanted to do some
information architecture work on your
website, I. Go and do a screaming
Frog poll of your entire thing.
Take that CSV and give it to a model
and have it analyze it and give
you some ideas about what it sees.
There are things that can give you
superpowers as someone that is an expert
if you use and leverage these tools in
the right way, because they are just
machine learning and that technology
has been around for a long time.
Shane Baglini: Yeah, agreed.
That's a great point.
Using the tools as ways to expand
your skillset, I think is, is
one of the messages that I'd
like to get across to people.
I'll never, ever claim to be a
mathematician or remotely good with
numbers, and so for me to have a tool to
be able to do financial analysis and do
cost per acquisition modeling and things
of that nature, that's invaluable to me.
That's where AI is like the best
thing ever because it's letting
me do things that I can't do.
Based on just who I am and how I'm wired.
The other thing too is that I've
found that a pretty large portion
of my AI use is using it to solve
the things that take mental energy,
but aren't a priority for me.
So, you know, it could, it could
very well be like drafting, I dunno.
Thank you.
Page language.
After your RFI form, could I
do it in, in a half an hour?
I could.
Could I do it in 30 seconds
and get 80% of the way there?
I, I could, and that's saving me mental
energy to focus on other stuff, leading
people, teamwork dynamics, thi things
again, that AI can't replace that I
need the, the brain bandwidth to do.
So I use it every day on things like that,
on things that expand my skillset, but
I, I can't use it to mask the fact that.
I even have to check the numbers and
I'm not good at math, so like you can't
use it as a, a, a, a, be all, end all.
You can't use it as a bandaid for
things that you can't do or that
you're, you know, your brand can't
do, your messaging can't do there.
Those are foundational things that AI
can, that enhance once you start to
work on, on building that foundation.
Joel Goodman: And I think
it's key to understand what
this technology is best at.
Kind of like put it in tears, right?
It's like financial analysis.
You know what it's really good at?
You could have it just write a script
and have it execute the script and
then you know the script is gonna
run the exact same time every time.
It's going to give you
that data consistently.
Whenever you need that to happen, you
plug in your numbers and let it do it.
Versus like assuming that when you
go and ask it to, to conduct an
analysis, it's going to do that.
Like have it write a script,
it'll do it, and then.
You can execute it with, with
the lm you can execute it on your
own if you learn how to get in
the command line or whatever.
But like, there are ways to make sure
that it's doing things consistently
and it's doing things that you spend
less server cycles, you spend less
energy, um, you know, just from a,
from a sheer processing standpoint.
If it's writing a script once, rather
than trying to write a script internally,
maybe slightly different every single
time and then run the thing, you know,
and it's the same thing with, uh, it's
kind of like with prompt engineering for,
for different, uh, generative outputs.
You know, if you want it to be
consistent, you write a specific prompt
and you make sure that prompt gives
it some guidelines to do that, and it
will generate that text consistently
each time finding the ways to.
Put those guardrails in place for
things based on what large language
models are actually good at versus
what you're told they're good at,
or what the marketing has sold us.
Because generative text, I think, is one
of the most boring things that LLMs do.
Like, I mean, it's cool, it's very
cool, but it also is so prone to
error where writing, writing code.
In small subsets like full apps,
that's a different, then we can
talk about that some other time.
But like small scripts, automating
small things, like making sure
that certain routines are in place.
Those are the things that it's very,
very good at doing those, doing that
analysis, writing a script to do that
analysis, you know, that sort of thing.
So using it to do the things.
It's really good.
Um, and also kind of like cementing
it so that it's not changing that in
the future as models change, but it's
a skill A lot of people don't have.
What, because maybe you're not technical.
Maybe you know, you, you haven't looked
into it enough like, but there are things
that, that large language models are a
lot better at doing than other things.
And they're typically not the
ones that we've been sold.
Shane Baglini: I think for higher
ed and probably more industries,
we have so many things going on at
one time and so many initiatives
that we're trying to push forward.
I think a lot of times innovating
with AI gets left behind because of
deadlines, because of KPIs, because
of things that we're responsible for.
And so I would just, again, drive
home the message that if you're
seeing a lot about AI and you think,
I'm not, I'm not doing any of this.
I'm behind, I, I, I gotta catch up.
You're right where you should be because.
You are focusing on other things.
You're focusing on things related
to the mission of your institution.
You're focused on helping students.
You're focused on engaging with donors.
Whatever area of higher ed you're working
in that you think I need to catch up on
AI to do my job better, it's probably
not the case because the things that
you're doing, building relationships,
displaying emotional intelligence, you
know, leadership qualities, team building.
All of those things that you focus on
can't be replaced by ai, and therefore
you can't be replaced by AI if you don't,
if you don't think you're up to speed.
So I would just enc, I just
encourage everybody to chill out,
relax, do it at your own pace.
If your organization or your
institution can allow you to block
two hours on a Friday afternoon
to experiment with ai, if you have
it in your schedule, that's great.
But a lot of the pain points I hear
from colleagues around the industry is
that I don't have time to do this stuff.
We are burning the candle at both ends.
We're short staffed, short on resources.
I just don't have time for this.
And so that's where I feel like this
kind of pressure, this pressure complex
is coming from that, that I, you know.
Constant ai, onslaught of thought
leadership and hot takes and all this,
this stuff about ai, it's, it, it, it, it
can make you feel that way and I'm just
would encourage people to not feel that
way 'cause I'm in the same boat as you.
Everybody's in the same boat.
And I think it, the reality of
what higher ed marketers and higher
ed in general do and go through
on a daily basis is being sort of
pushed aside for AI implementation.
Joel Goodman: If you need help figuring
out how to use these technologies,
there are plenty of people that
would love to help you do it.
Get in touch with me, subscribe to
the newsletter, and I'll be happy to
connect you with folks or help you
myself if that's something I can do.